<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a souldier of good place in Ireland, to his friend in London touching the notable victorie of her Maiesties forces there, against the Spaniards, and Irish rebels: and of the yeelding vp of Kynsale, and other places there held by the Spanyards.</title>
            <author>I. E., fl. 1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852797</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21067)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 832:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a souldier of good place in Ireland, to his friend in London touching the notable victorie of her Maiesties forces there, against the Spaniards, and Irish rebels: and of the yeelding vp of Kynsale, and other places there held by the Spanyards.</title>
                  <author>I. E., fl. 1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by T. Creede?] for Symon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on D3r: I.E.; a variant has 'J.E.'.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Egerton, later Earl of Bridgewater.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1595-1612.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18146:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18146:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER from a Souldier of good place in Ireland, to his friend in London, touching the <hi>notable Victorie of her Maiesties Forces</hi> there, againſt the Spaniards, and Iriſh Rebels:</p>
            <p>And of the yeelding vp of <hi>Kynſale,</hi> and other places there held by the Spanyards.</p>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted for Symon Waterſon. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18146:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18146:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull my eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall good friend, Sir W. D. <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir in my laſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>19.</hi> of December I wrote to you at large of the arriuall of the newe ſupplie of Spaniards at Caſtel-haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temore, and Beerha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and beginnings to fortifie, in all thoſe thrée important pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Likewiſe that Sir <hi>Richard Leuiſon</hi> towing out of <hi>Kinſale</hi> Hauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt winde &amp; weather, fought with them within Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Hauen moſt valiantly, and of their ſhips being ſixe, ſunke and made vnſeruiceable fiue: the men being moſt landed before hee could come to them, by reaſon of the weather, and beating vpon him very dangerouſly from the land with their ordinance. That they were ſaid to be <hi>2000.</hi> in number, with great ſtore of ordinance and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, &amp; that as they reported, ſome thouſande moe were comming after. That a great part of the Iriſhry of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> becommen Rebels of new, were reuolted to them, and receiued into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King of <hi>Spaines</hi> pay. That <hi>Odonell</hi> with good Forces of horſe and foote out of the North, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18146:3"/>
the benefit of the then extreame &amp; ſudden froſt, gat paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage almoſt vnlooked for by himſelfe, and ſlipping by the Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter</hi> (who was ſent to impeach him) with ſuch forces as could be ſpared from the Army) was ioyned with them. That <hi>Tyrone,</hi> with <hi>O Rourck, Redman Bourck, Mac Guyre, Mac Mahone, Randal Mac Surley, Oconor, Slygoes</hi> brother, <hi>Tyrrel,</hi> the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Lixenho,</hi> and the reſt of the old fugitiue Rebels of <hi>Munſter,</hi> with the greateſt and choiſeſt force that was euer amaſſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> were drawne nere our Camp. And that theſe all, together with ſixe Enſignes of thoſe newly arriued Spaniards, in all to the number of <hi>6000.</hi> foote, and <hi>500</hi> horſe, by <hi>Powle,</hi> were on foote ready to march towardes <hi>Kynſale</hi> and our Campe, with intent and moſt aſſured confident hope with helpe of them in the Town, which ſhould haue ſalyed out on the Campe, vpon the attempt of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and <hi>Odonell,</hi> and were aboue <hi>2000.</hi> Spaniards, almoſt all old ſouldiers, aſwell to reléeue and reſcue the Towne, as to remoue our ſiege, and vtterly to breake, diſhonour, and defeate vs. And truely Sir, when I did then conſider, on the one ſide this great ſtrength, the newly ioyned men and horſes to bée all freſh, vigorous, and ſtrong, hauing all the Countrey ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them, abounding with victuals, forrages, armies, munition, and all furnitures: thoſe in the Towne, the moſt of them experienced ſouldiers, well armed, and in no ſuch want as was ſuppoſed: On the other ſide, our men in numbers ſcant equall to them, all almoſt tyred and wearied out with the miſerie of a long Winters ſiege, our horſes decayed, leane and very weake, our beſt meanes of victuals and forrage likely to be cut from vs, with many other impediments whereof I ſpeake not; When I ſay, I well wayed and pondred with my ſelfe theſe poynts, and layde together withall, this one of great importance, that when we ſhould be forced (as it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18146:3"/>
was likely) to anſwere two forces at once, one from the Towne, another without, a great part of our men were like enough to ſhrink, or at leaſt not to ſtick firmely to vs (which by good coniectures I could make probable to you) Blame me not, if vpon theſe conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I wrote to you then ſomewhat diſtruſtfully of our eſtate, as ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king indéed our liues and honors, this ſeruice, and by conſequence this whole Countrey likely to be put to an vnequall iumpe. And ſo may I well ſay they were, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by the goodneſſe of GOD eſpecially, and by the moſt vigilant circumſpection and valiant prowes of our worthy Generall, things out of theſe difficulties haue now ſorted to ſo happy ſucceſſe, as by that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you ſhall ſufficiently perceiue. To continue therefore my accuſtomed Relation to you, and to begin from that ſaid day of the <hi>19.</hi> of December, It may pleaſe you to knowe, that on Sunday the <hi>20.</hi> wée ſtill plying our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to the Towne, with face and ſhew as though we nothing cared for <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his companie, at night certaine intelligence was brought vs, that he would bée the next night within a myle and a halfe of vs, with all the aboue recyted Forces. And accordingly vpon Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the <hi>21.</hi> towardes night, hée ſhewed himſelfe with moſt part of his horſe and foote, on a hill betwéene our Campe and <hi>Corke,</hi> a myle off vs. At which time ſéeing two Regiments of our foote, and ſome horſe drawne out of our Campe, and making a reſolute march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him, hée fell backe to the other ſide of the hill, where hée encamped that night, ſtrengthened with a faſtneſſe of wood and water. Whereby though his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre might bée imputed to ſome touch of credite, yet had hee this aduantage, that hée might kéepe from our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie all paſſages and meanes for forrage: The other ſide ouer the Riuer of <hi>Ownibuoye</hi> béeing wholly at his diſpoſition, by reaſon of the generall reuolt of thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18146:4"/>On Tueſday the <hi>22.</hi> ſome of <hi>Tyrones</hi> horſe and foote made ſhewe againe in the place where they had done the day before, and that night were ſome of their horſe, and <hi>500.</hi> foote diſcouered, ſearching if they might finde fit way to the Towne.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday the <hi>23.</hi> aſwell by intelligence other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as by letters of <hi>Don Iohn d'l Aquila,</hi> Generall of the Spaniards, and Captaine of the Towne newly intercepted, we found that he had importuned <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his company very much, to giue an attempt vpon our Campe; inumating vnto them his owne neceſſitie, and likelyhood to bee ſhortly forced within the Towne, their faithfull promiſes to ſuccour him, the facilitie &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted ſucceſſe of the enterpriſe, he aſſuring them, that our numbers could not be but much leſſened, and thoſe that were remaining, greatly decayed and weakened with the long winter ſiege, ſo that it was not poſſible we ſhould be able to maintaine ſo much ground as we had taken whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſtrength was full, if they on the one ſide, and he on the other put vs well too it: which he for his part promiſed them aſſuredly to doo very ſoundly from the Towne, whenſoeuer they ſhould thinke fit to doo the like from their Campe. And it ſéemeth that vpon this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe they tooke their determinate reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for this courſe, and to put it in execution with all ſpeed, either that night or the next at the furtheſt. Thoſe of the Towne in the meane time gaue vs alarums, made Sallies, and did by all meanes what they could to kéepe our men in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all trauell, that they might be the leſſe able for reſiſtance when this attempt ſhould come to be performed. The Lord Deputie till now applied himſelfe in ſhow wholly towards the Towne, but indéed not meaning any force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able effectuall attempt vpon it, till he ſawe what would become of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his Forces.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18146:4"/>and therefore hadde an eſpeciall eye, by continuall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piall, vpon his meanings, and leſt ſuddaine hurt ſhould be taken from him, or the Towne, if both he without, and they within ſhould inuade at once, he made Fortes and Barracadoes, heightned the ditches, déepened the Trenches, ſtopped and ſtrengthened all the Auenues to the Towne, hadde the whole Army in a readineſſe vppon euery ſuddaine warning, and kept ſtrong and watchfull guardes alwayes in all places. And now late in the night of this Wedneſday, the thrée and twentieth day, being aſſuredly enfourmed of their intent of attempt vpon his Campe that night, or the morrow after, his Lo. gaue order to ſtrengthen the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary guards, and to put the reſt of his Army in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but not as yet into Armes: commaunding that the Regiment volant, which was a ſquadron of viii. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of foote, ſelected out of al the old Bands, conducted by Sir <hi>Hen. Poore,</hi> and appointed to be alwayes in a readines to anſwere all Alarames, and therefore exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from all other duties, ſhould draw out beyond the weſt parte of the Campe, and there ſtand in Armes, not farre from the maine guard of horſe.</p>
            <p>A litle before the breake of day Sir <hi>Ric. Greame,</hi> who had the guard of horſe that night, ſent the Lo. Deputie word, that the ſkowts had diſcouered the rebels matches in great numbers, whervpon his Lo. cauſed the Armie preſently to arme, and <hi>300.</hi> choiſe men to be drawne out of the quarter, where the Earle of <hi>Thomond</hi> and <hi>3.</hi> other Regiments lay, to make ſtand betweene that quarter, and the Fort vppon the weſt hill, himſelfe with Sir <hi>George Carow,</hi> Lo. Preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Wingfield,</hi> marſhall of <hi>Ireland,</hi> aduanced forward towards the ſkowt, and hauing giuen order to <hi>Sir Hen. Dauers</hi> Liuetennant generall of the horſe, for the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of thoſe troopes, ſent the Marſhall, to take view of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18146:5"/>
the Enemy, who ſent word he was aduanced horſe and foote néere the toppe of the hill, where the Erle of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> firſt quartered, within leſſe then <hi>2.</hi> muſket ſhotte of the towne. Whervpon the Lo: deputie calling to him ſir <hi>Oliuer Lambert</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Connaught,</hi> who bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there without Charge, was commaunded to attend his Lo. that day, made choiſe of a péece of ground bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene that and the towne, of good aduauntage, both to embattel, and fight, as hauing on the backe a Trench drawne from the Earle of <hi>Thomonds</hi> quarter, and ſo ſecured from the Towne: And on the front, a boggiſh glyn paſſable with horſe only at one foord: The ground wheron the Enemy muſt haue drawn in groſſe to force the paſſage flanckfered from the Earles quarter by the canon, and ſituate in the midſt of allour Forces, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned word to the Marſhall, that in that place hée was reſolued to giue the Enemy battel, if hée came forward: commaunding further, the Regiment of Sir <hi>H. Folya<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and thrée old Companies of the Regiment of Sir <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Saint-Iohn</hi> to bée brought thither, the reſt of the Army being al ready in Armes, together with fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sea-men, brought by Sir <hi>Richard Leueſon</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, when, and what, he ſhould command.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Tirone,</hi> whoſe meaning ouer night, was, to haue béene with vs before daie, and as wee ſince learned, to haue put al the Spaniards into the Towne, with viii. hundred of the beſt Iriſh vnder <hi>Tirrell</hi> ſéeing it now faire day light, and diſcouering the Marſhall and Sir <hi>Hen: Dauers</hi> to bée aduaunced with all the horſe, and Sir <hi>Hen: Poer</hi> with his Regiment, ſtopt at the foote of the hill, and anon, thinking it to bée no day for him, reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Troopes he had aduanced againe, to the bodie of his Armie beyond the Foord. Preſently the Marſhall ſent the Lord Deputie word, that the Enemy retired
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18146:5"/>
in ſome diſorder, wherevpon his Lo: commanding the forenamed troops to folow him with al ſpéed, aduanced himſelfe into the head of al, to ſee with his owne eie, the maner of the enemy, &amp; in what ſort thereupon he might determine to procéede. But before he could, either well view, or direct, a violent ſtorme, during ſome quarter of an hower, gaue the enemy oportunitie, not yet perfectly diſconered, to drawe off ouer a plaine in three great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of foote, all their horſe in the Rere, and the wings with all their other looſe men fallen vp into the head. Which the L. Deputie, the day now clearing, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and dicſouering, by this their diſorderly March, that they were in feare, being certified alſo, that there was not before them any place of ſo good aduantage to make head on, as thoſe they had paſſed and quited, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to follow, and to ſée what profit might be made of an enemy thus troubledly retiring. Whereupon diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching preſently Sir <hi>Geo. Carew,</hi> Lo. Preſident of Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter with thrée cornets of horſe backe to the Campe, to attend there againſt the Towne, and whatſoeuer other attempt, becauſe he was to be the fitteſt Commaunder in his Lo. abſence, and becauſe there had otherwiſe no horſes bene left in the Campe, himſelfe hauing with him, in al, betwéene thrée and foure hundred horſe, and vnder <hi>1200.</hi> foot, made after the Enimy. And aduancing ſome mile further on, preſſed him ſo hard, that he was forced to ſtand firme in thrée bodies vpon a foorde of a bogge (which bogge to aſſaile them, we muſt of neceſſity paſſe) and in all apparance, with a Reſolution there to abide vs and fight. They maintained a good ſkirmiſh on our ſide the Bogge, with their looſe wings, newly drawne out of their bodies, and hurt ſome of our men and horſes, till with our wings they were at length bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten backe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18146:6"/>The Marſhall being ſomewhat aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nced, eſpied a Foord, a muſket ſhot off on the left hand, neglected by their foote, and onely guarded by their horſe: whereof aduertiſing the Lord Deputy, with deſire of leaue to force them that way: the Lord Deputy approouing it, and commaunding to drawe vp drawe vp the foote with all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the firſt wings of foote once arriued, ſeconded with ſir <hi>Henry Poers</hi> regiment, the Marſhall, with the earle of <hi>Clanricard,</hi> who neuer ceaſed vrging to fight, taking with them ſir <hi>Richard Greame,</hi> and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of horſe: with them, and thoſe foote, forcing the enemies horſe that kept the paſſage, paſſed ouer, and with that aduantage, finding themſelues ſide by ſide with the enemies battell, and further on then their rere, charged their battell in flanke, but finding them to ſtand firme, whéeled about. At which the enemies ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king corage, drew on their horſe, with a cry to a charge, who came on brauely within fiftie or ſixtie paces of our horſe, and there after their country faſhion ſtopped, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their ſtaues, and railingly vaunting, but durſt charge no further. Which the Lord Deputy ſéeing, ſent preſently ouer the Foorde to them his owne cornet of horſe, vnder ſir <hi>William Godolphin,</hi> and the Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents cornet vnder Captaine <hi>Minſhow,</hi> (which twoo cornets he had appoynted before, to kéepe ſtil a groſſe in the Rere, to anſwer all accidents) together with twoo af our thrée bodies of foote vnder ſir <hi>Iohn Barkeley</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iant maior of the Campe. Wherevpon the Marſhall and Earle of <hi>Clanrickard</hi> ſeeing a ſecond at hand, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting themſelues with Sir <hi>Henrie Dauers,</hi> hauing with him Captaine <hi>Taffe,</hi> Captaine <hi>Flemming,</hi> and other companies of horſe, charged againe the Enemies horſe, who not abiding the ſhocke, fledde. At the ſight whereof, the battell diſmaying, our menne thought
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18146:6"/>
it better to charge againe vpon them, then to follow the horſe, and ſo coragiouſly doing, vtterly brake them. The rereward of the Enemie, in which was <hi>Tyrrell,</hi> and all the Spaniards, ſtoode firme vpon the bogge on the right hand, vnto whom, within caliuer ſhot, the Lorde Deputie had drawne vp our Rere, which was Sir <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Saint Iohns</hi> 3. companies, commanded by Captaine <hi>Roe,</hi> in abſence of ſir <hi>Oliuer,</hi> (diſpatched few dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Lord Deputie, and Counſaile, for ſpeciall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to her Maieſty) charging him firſt, not to ſtir, till he receiued direction from him. But ſéeing <hi>Tirrell,</hi> and the Spaniards drawing betwéene our horſe, béeing on the execution, and the bodies of our foote, his Lo. hauing hitherto, by direction, ſet al other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſwords on work, himſelfe now in the head of our ſaid Rere, where he had before reſolued to fight, charged the Enemy in flancke, and put them to a diſorderly retreite after their fellows to the toppe of the next hill, where they made ſtand a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while. But the Iriſh quiting the Spaniards, the Spaniardes in ſhort time were broken by the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties horſe, commaunded by ſir <hi>William Godolphin,</hi> and moſt of them ſlaine. The vantgarde of the Enemy, with all the looſe wings, which were many, ſéeing what happened, threw away their armes (and all our men being otherwiſe buſie) eſcaped. The chiefe Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Spaniards, <hi>Don Alonſo d'Ocampo</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoner, with three Captaines, ſixe Alferrez, and fortie ſouldiers. <hi>Tirone,</hi> and <hi>Odonell,</hi> with the reſt of the Iriſh Lords, ran apace, and ſaued themſelues. Thoſe of the battell were almoſt all ſlaine, and there were (of the Iriſh Rebelles onely) found dead in the place, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout twelue hundred bodies, and about eight hundred were hurt, whereof many dyed that night: and the chace continuing almoſt two miles, was left off, our men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18146:7"/>
being tyred with killing. The Enemy loſt two thouſand Armes brought to reckning, beſides great numbers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezeled, al their powder and drummes, and ix. enſigns, whereof <hi>6.</hi> Spaniſh. Thoſe of the Iriſh that were taken priſoners, being brought to the Campe, though they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ranſome, were all hanged. On our ſide, onely one man was ſlaine, the Cornet of ſir <hi>Richard Greame.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Dauers</hi> was hurt with a ſword ſlightly: ſir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Godolphin</hi> a little raced on the thigh with a hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Captaine <hi>Crofts</hi> the Skowt-maſter with a ſhot in the back, &amp; not aboue ſixe moe common ſouldiers hurt. Many of our horſes were killed, and moe hurt. And thus were they vtterly ouerthrowne, who but the very night before, were ſo braue and confident of their owne good ſucceſſe, as that they reckoned vs already theirs, and as wée ſince haue vnderſtoode, were in contention whoſe priſoner the Lord Deputy ſhould be, whoſe the the Lorde Preſident, and ſo of the reſt. The Earle of <hi>Clanrickard</hi> carried himſelfe this day very valiantly, and after the retreite ſounded, was Knighted by the Lorde Deputy, in the field amongſt the dead bodies. So did all the reſt of the Captaines, Officers, and Souldiers, named and vnnamed, and eſpecially the Lo. Deputy himſelfe, who brake, in perſon, vpon the floure of the army the Spaniards, and omitted no duety of a wiſe diligent Conductor and valiant ſouldier. Vpon the fight ended, he preſently called together the Army, and with prayers, gaue God thankes for the victorie. A victorie indéede giuen by the God of Hoſtes, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous in our eyes, if all circumſtances be duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and of ſuch conſequence for the preſeruation and aſſuraunce to her Maieſtie, of this déepely endangered kingdome, as I leaue to wiſer conſideration, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe with this, that I ſée the God of power and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18146:7"/>
might, diſpoſed to protect the iuſt cauſe of his ſeruaunt, our gratious Quéene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> againſt the pride, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and powerful diſdain of the greateſt potentates, hir enemies. To him be the glorie.</p>
            <p>After this glorious victorie thus valiantly atchieued, the Lord Deputy the ſame day haſted to his campe, leſt any thing (in his abſence) might happely haue béene at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted there. But, not finding the Ennemy to haue made any ſally, which indéede had béene but vaine for him, conſidering the ſmall fruit he reaped by them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, euery one that he made hitherto redounding ſtil to his owne detriment and loſſe, and euery place of our Camp, at this time, being ſo wel and ſufficiently ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and prouided for againſt him as is ſayd before.</p>
            <p>The next day his Lordſhip commaunded Captayne <hi>Bodlegh</hi> Trench-maiſter generall of the Campe, who as well in the fight, as in the workes, had deſerued ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commendation, to ſée the formerly begunne Forte and platforms, to be vndertaken againe, and néerer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches to be caſt out towardes the towne. But after fiue or ſixe dayes labour <hi>Don Iohn d' lAquila,</hi> captaine of the Towne and Forces within, offered a parlée, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Drumme <hi>maior</hi> of the Towne with a ſealed let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Lord Deputy, by which he required, that ſome gentleman of ſpeciall truſt and ſufficiencie might be ſent into the towne from his Lordſhip, to conferre with him, whom he would acquaint with ſuch conditions, as hée then ſtoode vpon. His Requeſt being aſſented vnto by his Lordſhip, ſir <hi>William Godolphin</hi> was imployed in the negotiation, which was carried in this forte, word for word, as it is taken out of the originalls here, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Iohn</hi> tolde ſir <hi>William,</hi> that hauing found the Lord Deputy (whome he termed the Viceroy) although a ſharpe and powerfull, yet an honorable Enemy, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18146:8"/>
the Iriſh, not onely weake and barbarous, but (as hée feared) perfidious friendes, he was ſo farre in his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions reconciled to the one, and diſtaſted with the other, as did inuite him to make an ouerture of ſuch a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition as might be ſafe and profitable for the State of <hi>England,</hi> with leaſt preiudice to the Crowne of <hi>Spaine,</hi> by deliuering into the Viceroy his power, the Towne of <hi>Kynſale,</hi> with all other places in <hi>Ireland,</hi> held by the Spaniſh, ſo as they might depart on honorable termes, fitting ſuch men of warre, as are not (by neceſſity) infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to receiue conditions, but willingly induced, for iuſt reſpects to diſ-ingage themſelues, and to relinquiſh a people, by whom their King and Maſter had bene ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly abuſed, (if not betrayed.) That if the Viceroy liked to entertaine further parley touching this point, he would firſt be pleaſed to vnderſtand them rightly, &amp; to make his propoſitions ſuch as might be ſutable, to men thorowly reſolued, rather to bury themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and to endure a thouſand deaths, then to giue way to one Article of accord, that ſhuld taſte of baſenes or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, being ſo confident of their preſent ſtrength, and the royall Second of Spaine, that they ſhould make no doubt of yéelding good accompt of themſelues and their Intereſt in this Kingdome, but that a iuſt diſdaine, and ſpléene conceiued againſt the nation, diſſwaded them from being further engaged for it, then of force they muſt, Sir <hi>Wil. Godolphin</hi> being commaunded by the L. Deputie onely, to receiue <hi>Don Iohns</hi> propoſitions and demamaunds. Hauing made his L. and Counſel this Relation, was by them returned with the anſwere following. That howbeit the Lord Deputie hauing lately defeated their ſuccours, didde ſo well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his owne ſtrength and their weakeneſſe as made him nothing doubt of forcing them within a ſhort time,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18146:8"/>
whom he did know to be preſſed with vnreſiſtable difficulties, how much ſoeuer they laboured to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and conceale the ſame, yet knowing that her ſacred Maieſtie out of her gracious and mercifull diſpoſition would eſteeme the glory of her victory to be blemiſhed by a voluntary effuſion, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate expence of Chriſtian bloud, was content to entertaine this offer of agréement, ſo as it might be concluded, vnder ſuch honorable articles for her highnes as the aduauntage ſhe had againſt them gaue reaſon to demaund: being the ſame which are ſette downe in the Articles of agréement follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſigned by the Lord Deputie, and <hi>Don Iohn</hi> &amp; others: ſauing that there was in them beſides, the leauing of his treaſure, munition, artillery, and the Quéenes naturall Subiects to her diſpoſicion, all which points hée did peremptorely refuſe, with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant aſſeueracion that both he and all his would rather indure the laſt of miſery then be found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo foule a Treaſon againſt the honour of his Prince and the reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his profeſſion, though hée ſhould find himſelfe vnable to ſubſiſte, much more now, when hée might not onely hope to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine the burden of the warre for a time, but with patience and conſtancie in the end to ouercome it. That he tooke it ſo ill, to bée miſunderſtood in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Articles of that nature propounded vnto him, as were they but once againe remembred in the Capitulacion, the Viceroy ſhould from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth vſe the aduantage of his ſword and not the benefite of his former offers: adding, that the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy might rather thinke to haue made a good and profitable purchaſe for the Crowne of England,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18146:9"/>
if with the expence of <hi>200000</hi> Duckats hée had procured <hi>Don Iohn</hi> to quite his intereſt and footing but in Baltymore alone, to ſay nothing of Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale, Caſtell-hauen, and Beerehauen: for (ſaid he) ſuppoſe that all we with the reſt of our places here had periſhed, yet would that <hi>Pen Inſula</hi> (beyng ſtrong in it owne nature, bettered by our arte and induſtrie, prouided as it is of victuals, muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and good ſtore of Artillerie) preſerue vnto the King of Spaine a ſafe and commodious port for the arriuall of his Fléete, and be able to mayntaine it ſelfe againſt á land Armie of ten thouſand, vntill Spaine (being ſo déepely engaged) did in honour reléeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which would drawe on a more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inuaſion then the firſt, being vndertaken vpon falſe groundes, at the inſtance of a baſe and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people, who in diſcouering their weakenes and want of power, haue armed the King my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to relie vpon his owne ſtrength, beyng tied in honour to reléeue his people that are engaged, and to cancell the memory of our former diſaſter. But this was ſpoken (ſaid he) in caſe the Viceroy were able to force this town, as I aſſure my ſelfe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, hauing vpon mine Honour within theſe wals at this inſtant, aboue two thouſand fighting men, that are ſtrong and able, beſides thoſe, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing béen ſicke and hurt, recouer dayly: the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of theſe, compoſed of old Souldiers, which fall not but by the ſword, and thoſe that were new, beyng now both trayned to their Armes &amp; growne acquainted with the Climate, are more able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure then at the firſte: our meanes as good as they haue béene any times theſe two monethes, ſuch as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18146:9"/>
the Spaniardes can well away withall, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſuffize vs for thrée moneths more. We lodge in good warme houſes, haue ſtore of munition, and (which is beſt of all) ſtand well aſſured that our ſuccours wil bée ſhortly here. To bée playne, wée preſerue our men, and reſerue our ſtrength the beſt wée may, hoping to front you in a breach, which if our harts fayle vs not, we haue hands and breaſts enough to ſtop againſt treble your forces: though I will giue the Viceroy this right, That his men are paſſing good, but ſpent and tyred out with the miſery of a Winter ſiege, which he hath obſtinatly maintayned beyond my expectacion, but with ſuch caution, and vpon ſo good guard, as hauing nicely watched all aduauntages, I could neuer faſten a Sallie yet vpon him, but with loſſe to my ſelfe: wherein I muſte acknowledge my hopes decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that grounding on ſome errour in his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, promiſed my ſelf the defeate of at leaſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men at one blowe. But when wée méete on the breach, I am confident on good reaſon, to lay fiue hundred of your beſt men on the earth, and reſt hopeful that the loſſe of thoſe will make a great hole in an Armie that hath already ſuffred ſo much extremitie.</p>
            <p>But to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude our buſineſſe, the king my Maſter ſent me to aſſiſt the Condées, <hi>Oneale</hi> &amp; <hi>Odonnell,</hi> preſuming on their promiſe, that I ſhould haue ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them within few daies of the arriuall of his forces. I expected long in vaine, ſuſtained the Viceroyes Armie, ſaw them drawne to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt head they could poſſibly make, lodged within two myles of Kynſale, reenforced with certaine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18146:10"/>
companies of Spanyards, euery houre promiſing to releeue vs, and beeing ioyned together to force your campes, ſawe them at laſt broken with a handfull of men, blowne aſunder into diuers parts of the world, <hi>O Donnell</hi> into Spaine, <hi>Oneale</hi> to the furtheſt of the North, ſo as now I finde no ſuch Condées <hi>in rerum natura</hi> (for thoſe were the very wordes hee vſed) as I came to ioyne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and therefore haue moued this accord, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſingage the King my Maiſter from aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting a people ſo vnable in themſelues, that the whole burden of the warre muſt lie vpon him, and ſo perfidious, as perhaps might bee induced in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall of his fauour, at laſt to betray him. Vpon relation made by Sir <hi>VVilliam Godolphin</hi> to the Lord Deputie and Councell, of theſe offers of <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> which at ſeuerall conferences had beene brought to ſuch heads, as are ſpoken of before: it was thought good, for diuerſe important reaſons, to procéed roundly to the agréement. For whereas in the propoſitions by him made; there was not any thing that admitted exceptions on our part, but onely, that he required to carrie with him his ordinance, munition, and treaſure, that beeing no way preiudiciall to the maine ſcope or drift of our Treatie, which chéefely reſpected the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good and ſafetie of the kingdome, deſerued not almoſt to be thought vpon. Beſides that, the Treaſure béeing at the firſt but a hundred thouſand Duckats, with foure monethes payment of ſo many men, and other neceſſarie deductions, could not but bee very néere waſted; and that little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynder, more fit for a prey to the poore ſouldiour,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18146:10"/>
after his tedious trauell, than for a clauſe in the compoſition. Furthermore, how needfull it was to embrace this accord, may clearely bee ſeene by whoſoeuer conſidereth the ſtate of our Armie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vtterly tyred: how full of daunger and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie it was to attempt a breach defended by ſo many hands: how long time it might haue coſt vs, if wee had lodged in the Breach, before wee could haue carried the Towne, it beeing full of ſtrong caſtles: how her Maieſties ſhips and others lying in the harbour, ſhould haue béen forced ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to forſake vs for want of victuals: how by a long contrarietie of winds, our ſelues were not prouided for aboue ſixe daies, at the time of this parley, though within fewe dayes after good ſtore arriued: it being indéed worthy of obſeruation, that by her Maieſties great care, &amp; the dilligence of her miniſters, ſo good prouidence was vſed, as, though this deſcent of Spanyards drew into that quarter all the forces of the kingdome which could be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all which were onely to liue by prouiſion out of England; notwithſtanding all the difficulties of tranſportation, in ſo vnſeaſonable a time, no noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wants were found in the Armie, but that which is vnſeparable from a Winter ſiege, in that Climate: that we had neyther munition nor Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie left but for one batterie in one place at once, fiue of our péeces being before crazed: and finally, that if we had miſſed of our purpoſe, the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey had béen hazarded. Furthermore, that which ſeemeth of greateſt conſequence to induce his Lordſhip to this agréement, was: That the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyards in Baltymore Caſtle-hauen and Beere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauen,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18146:11"/>
by vertue of this contract were likewiſe to ſurrender thoſe places, and depart the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which would haue prooued a matter of more difficultie, and haue drawne on a long warre in a corrupted kingdome, to root them out, béeing ſtrongly fortified and well ſtored with victuals, munition, and artillerie, for that of neceſſitie the Armie for ſome ſpace, muſt haue reſted, and in the end haue beene conſtrained after a new ſupplie of al neceſſaries, to her Maieſties intollerable charge, to tranſport themſelues thither by ſea, the way by land being altogether vnpaſſbale. In which time, their ſuccours out of Spaine in all likelyhood, would haue béene come vnto them, the king being ſo farre ingaged in his honour to ſecond his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and we barred of that proſecution of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, which now by this Agréement we may whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entend.</p>
            <p>The Treatie therefore was thus concluded, as by the Articles enſuing, ſigned on both parts, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <head>Mountioye.</head>
                        <p>IN the town of Kynſale, in the kingdome of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the ſecond day of the month of Ianuarie, <hi>1601,</hi> betwéen the noble Lords, the Lord <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye,</hi> Lord Deputie, and Generall in the kingdome of Ireland, for her Maieſty the Quéen of England, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>and <hi>Don Iohn d'L Aquila,</hi> Captaine and Campe-maiſter,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18146:11"/>
Generall and Gouernour of the Armie of his Maieſtie the king of Spaine, the ſaid Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie being encamped, &amp; beſieging the ſaid towne, and the ſaid <hi>Don Iohn</hi> within it, for iuſt reſpects, and to auoid ſhedding of blood, theſe conditions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing were made betwéene the ſaid Lords Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and their campes, with the Articles which follow.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, That the ſaid <hi>Don Iohn d'L Aquila</hi> ſhall quit the places which he holds in this kingdome, as well of the towne of Kynſale, as thoſe which are held by the ſoldiers vnder his command in Caſtle-hauen, Baltymore, and in the caſtle at Béerhauen, and other parts, to the ſaid Lord Deputie, or to whome he ſhall appoint: giuing him ſafe tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſufficient for the ſaide people, of Ships and victuals, with the which the ſayd <hi>Don Iohn</hi> with them may go for Spain, if he can at one time, if not, in two ſhippings.</p>
                        <p>Item that the Souldiers at this preſent being vnder the commaunde of <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhall not beare armes againſt her Maieſtie the Quéene of England, wherſoeuer ſupplies ſhall come from Spaine, till the ſaid ſouldiers be vnſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſome of the Ports of Spaine, being diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched as ſoone as may be by the Lord Deputie, as hee promiſeth vpon his faith and honor.</p>
                        <p>For the accompliſhing whereof the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie offereth to giue frée paſſeport to the ſaid <hi>Don Iohn</hi> and his army, aſwell Spaniards as other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18146:12"/>
whatſoeuer that are vnder his commaund, and that he may depart with all the things he hath, Armes, Municions, Money, Enſignes diſplaied, Artillery &amp; other whatſoeuer prouiſions of warre, and any kind of ſtuffe, aſwell that which is in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlehauen, as Kynſale and other parts.</p>
                        <p>Item that they ſhal haue ſhips and victuals ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for their money, according and at the prices which here they vſe to giue. That al the people and the ſaid things may be ſhipped if it be poſſible at one time, if not, at two: and that to be within the time aboue named.</p>
                        <p>Item that if by contrary windes or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions there ſhal ariue at any Port of theſe kingdomes of Ireland or England, any ſhippes of theſe in which the ſaid men goe, they be entreated as frendes, and may ride ſafely in the harbor, and be victualed for their mony, and haue moreouer things which they ſhall néed to furniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their voyage.</p>
                        <p>Item, during the time that they ſhall ſtay for ſhipping, victuals ſhalbe giuen to <hi>Don Iohns</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, at iuſt and reaſonable rates.</p>
                        <p>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that of both parts ſhalbe ceſſation of armes, and ſecurity that no wrong be offred any one.</p>
                        <p>Item, That the Ships in which they ſhall goe for Spayne may paſſe ſafely by any other Ships whatſoeuer of her Maieſtie the Quéene of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18146:12"/>
England: and ſo ſhall they of the ſayd Quéene and her Subiects by thoſe that ſhall goe from hence: &amp; the ſayde Shippes being arriued in <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall returne aſſoone as they haue vnſhipped their men without any impediment giuen them by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, or any other perſon in his name, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall ſhewe them fauour, and helpe them if they néede any thinge, and for ſecuritie of this, they ſhall giue into the Lorde Deputies handes Thrée Captaines ſuch as hee ſhall chooſe.</p>
                        <p>For the ſecuritie of the perfourmance of theſe Articles, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> offereth that hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſweare to accompliſh this Agreement: and likewiſe ſome of the Captaines of his charge ſhall ſweare and confirme the ſame in a ſeuerall writing,</p>
                        <p>Item that hee in perſon ſhall abide in this Kingdome where the Lord Deputie ſhall appoint till the laſt ſhipping vpon his Lordſhippes word: and if it happen that his people be ſhipped all at once, the ſayde <hi>Don Iohn</hi> ſhall goe in the ſame Fléete without any Impediment giuen him. But rather the Lord Deputie ſhall giue a good Shippe in which he may goe, and if his ſayd men be ſent in twoo ſhippinges, then he ſhall goe in the laſt.</p>
                        <p>And in like ſort the ſaide Lord Deputie ſhall ſweare and confirme, and giue his word in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of her Maieſtie the Quéene and his owne, to kéepe and accompliſh this Agréement, and ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord Preſident, the Lord Marſhall of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18146:13"/>
Campe, and thother of the Councell of State, and the Earles of <hi>Thomond</hi> &amp; <hi>Clanrykard</hi> ſhall ſweare and confirme the ſame in a ſeuerall writing.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>J</hi> promiſe and ſweare to accompliſh and keepe theſe Articles of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and promiſe the ſame likewiſe on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of his Maieſtie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique the Kinge my Maiſter.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Don John d'l A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>George Carew.</item>
                                 <item>Thomond.</item>
                                 <item>Clanrikard.</item>
                                 <item>R. Wingfeild.</item>
                                 <item>Ro. Gardemor.</item>
                                 <item>Geo. Bourcher.</item>
                                 <item>Rich. Liueſon.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo is this troubled Cloud, of moſt likely perillous danger for this time diſſolued, to her Maieſties moſt ſinguler renowme; Not ſo much for the glorie of the euent, as for her owne Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie and Princely reſolution, to leaue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vndone which might preſerue that Crowne, how deare ſo euer it coſt her; to the great honour of our Generall, Leaders, and Souldiers by land and Sea Actors therein, who, if it be well conſidered, that after the Enemies arriuall xxviij. Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18146:13"/>
it was xxvi. October before they could get all things readie to ſit downe nere the Towne: xxix. October before their Ordinance could play, And that by j. Nouember. they had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ricorren</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, And then vij. Nouember were driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhrewdly to diminiſh their ſtrength by ſending the L. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident from them with two Regiments of foote and <hi>325</hi> horſes againſt <hi>Odonell,</hi> That hee retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not till xxv. Nouember, his Companies <hi>26.</hi> And then that the Supplyes of <hi>Spaine</hi> were lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. That the moſt of our ſhipping that did vs ſpeciall ſeruice were gone towardes them, That <hi>Odonell</hi> was alreadie come, <hi>Tyron</hi> ſhortly after, and xx. December all in ſight: <hi>24</hi> beaten: That xxxj. December the Parley begunne, ij. Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie the Articles were ſworne: ix. the Towne yéelded. Theſe thinges (I ſay) conſidered, it cannot bée thought they ſpent any idle time, as by the Iournals alſo which I ſent you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore doth particulerly appeare. Nay, let it bée duely conſidered indéed, that the Towne though not regulerly fortified after the moderne ſort, yet was of ſtrong ſcituation, well walled, and rampierd of the old faſhion, and apt to receiue fit fortification, which the Enemie by his ſkill and leaſure had giuen it, both within the Towne and without, as being accounted of great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in fortification, and hauing béene a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it before our men could come néere much to moleſt him. And it may rather bee maruailed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuch an Enemie with ſuch a Companie, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, not béeing conſtrained by ſickeneſſe, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or other defect of prouiſion, and expecting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18146:14"/>
ſhortly (as himſelfe tearmeth it) a Royall ſupplie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhould ſo ſoone yéeld vp, not only it, but the other Caſtles, &amp; that of <hi>Baltymore</hi> eſpecially ſo important, ſo ſtrong, ſo fourniſhed to hould ſo long out, as by his owne acknowledgement ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth before. Well, going they are with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loane of ordinarie veſſels which they alſo pay for: for whome yea and almoſt for any enemie of leſſe qualitie than theſe, all auncient eſtate wiſedome would haue aduiſed to haue made and giuen them a goulden bridge to paſſe ouer, rather than they ſhould haue ſtayed longer vppon any Condition, much leſſe vpon doubtfull hope of a ſmall contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible pillage to haue béene gotten of them, which muſt néedes alſo haue béene bought with much blood, and with what further Charge and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to the mayne, God knoweth. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any perticuler humour may take it, I thinke <hi>Don Iohn</hi> (all Circumſtances conſidered) did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly for his King to leaue it: And for our part I take it a Seruice to haue béene moſt honourably perfourmed, with ſinguler euident profite, and all probabilitie of certaine future ſecuritie to our Prince and Countrey, and that otherwiſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bée conceaued off, of any that will indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iudge. The proofe whereof by the fruite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth here preſently to appeare, by the dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of her Maieſties Charge, daunting of the Rebels, quiet, comfort, and encouragement of the good, and before diſmayed Subiect, and will (I doubt not) but be generally felt with you there, by ſparing your men and monneys, and putting you out of feare hereafter, of your and our, and all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18146:14"/>
               <hi>Englands</hi> potent Enemie for his further attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this way. And this for this of the late victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and yéelding of the Towne, which is my purpoſed taſke vnto you at this time. As for that which was done from the firſt landing of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards till the fight, I referre you to the Iournals ſent you before. And for the generall courſe of the noble Lord Deputies whole procéedinges in this Land, ſince his firſt arriuall héere, I leaue it to others to bee treated of more at large hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, onely this I will now ſay in generall, let it bée but without humour iudicially conſidered, in what eſtate he found this Land, and to what hée hath now brought it, and there is none ſo vnindif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently affected, but muſt bee forced to confeſſe, <hi>Quantum mutatus ab illo!</hi> And héere I end my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the fight, and yéelding of the Towne, and whole quiting of all the Inuadors, with <hi>Salmaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da Spolia,</hi> an vnbloudie victorie of our part, moſt befitting a Virgin Quéene, and a Bacheler Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. And ſo doe betake you to the Almightie. At <hi>Corcke</hi> this <hi>13</hi> of <hi>Ianuarie, 1601.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. I. E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
